[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
hologography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of March 8
1999 this week we're going to listen to
the keynote address at the 25th
anniversary Mensa conference which was
held Saturday evening at the Holiday Inn
Hotel and Conference Center at Tinton
Falls New Jersey with the central New
Jersey Mensa group hello to you all
again if you happen to be listening to
the show first before we get started
with that I would like to say
congratulations to Britain and Samantha
there are two sixth grade students who
just won first place
in the science competition that they
entered right outside of Metropolitan
New York area and they just won that
first place award today using laser
pointers to create Holograms and you may
remember this group as they were the
first group to come into my lab to take
a workshop to make laser pointer
Holograms and one of the little boys
who's in the group Mike his hologram is
actually up as a picture on the
laser pointer page
so let's move on to the Mensa conference
and there's one thing I want to point
out
right right as I was introducing the
laser light show
I wanted to go over and turn the lights
out so that I could pass the laser beam
over everyone's heads in the ballroom
unfortunately I didn't want to record
the laser light show since it would just
turn out to be music anyway so what I
did is I turned the tape recorder off
of course I forgot to turn the tape
recorder back on again after the laser
light show is over so the second part or
the conclusion of the keynote address
was not recorded so we're going to
listen to it up until that point I'd
like to thank Steve Michael John Claire
Lonnie Anderson for sending in their
Holograms and Bert Myers I also had one
of your medical Holograms there as well
and they were very very well received
it was a great conference and everyone
loved looking at the Holograms
especially considering that they were
created using a inexpensive laser
pointer so let's move on to that I'm not
going to come back on after the show's
over so I will thank you now for tuning
in we'll get back to our guests either
next week or the week after and I hope
you tune in each week
keep up with news and general
information on the field of lasers and
Holograms right here at the internet's
laser and holography radio talk show
Hollow talk this is Frankie Freitas see
you next week
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can do this and
much more by attending one of Frank's
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five-week complete courses and
don't forget your newest Workshop laser
pointer holography located
the Northeast Extension of the
Pennsylvania Turnpike and Interstate 78
the studio is a quick non-stop drive
from the New York Philadelphia and
Baltimore Washington DC areas for more
information call the Studio's toll-free
hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending Frankie greatest holography
Workshop today
foreign
we're going to be taking a look at what
I hope is some very interesting things
for you tonight in fact you will be the
first group of people in the world to
see what you're going to see tonight
it's a whole new aspect of lasers and
holography several of you may actually
say that it's not possible to do this
but it is possible we've been doing it
for I'd say six or eight weeks now and I
had a few other holographers from Norway
send some work in that they confirm that
it's possible to do and the excuse me
cold fusion no it's not anything that
wouldn't that be something now maybe I
shouldn't build it up too much after
that
but what I wanted to do is save it for
you tonight to take a look at
um
and we'll get to that but first what I
want to do we're recording this
for a internet broadcast that's going to
broadcast this week I have a show on the
internet and we're going to have this up
for a week
and what I'd like to do is have Peggy
come up if you don't mind and give the
folks who are listening the whole talk
listeners I want to say hello to them as
well because they're listening to me
right now in their homes around the
world we have about 42 countries that
log on religiously to hear news about
lasers and holography from an artistic
and scientific standpoint each week so
Peg if you don't mind taking a minute or
two you can let everyone out there who's
listening right now not live but they
will be listening as of tomorrow evening
a little bit about your organization I
know you've been running this event
probably one of the longest ones in the
country so I want to take a few minutes
just to tell everyone what you're all
about
okay
um
we are present at an event called
snowball which is a regional Gathering
of American Mensa sponsored by Central
New Jersey Mensa Mensa is a high IQ
Society the qualifications board are to
test on a standardized test in the top
two percent of the population
this event is sort of like an annual
convention for our local group we have
people here in attendance from
California and Tennessee and New England
and of course New Jersey and
Pennsylvania and lots of other
surrounding states although I guess
that's about all of them New York New
England anywhere
which and Virginia we mustn't forget
Virginia uh we get together for the
weekend and we listen to fascinating and
interesting speakers and funny speakers
and tell each other jokes and play games
and uh party and hang out and and have a
good time for three days and then we go
back to the real world on Monday morning
um and this weekend our uh keynote
speaker as you know is uh Mr de Freitas
um he mentioned the fact that this is
snowball 25. Central New Jersey Mensa
has sponsored this particular convention
Regional gathering for 25 years in a row
we are the only single local group in
the United States that has done that so
we're very proud of that fact and we're
glad that we had uh
[Applause]
and we're happy to have had I think it's
uh how many
over 250 people are here enjoying this
weekend with us in lovely and Scenic
Tinton Falls New Jersey
thank you
thanks Becky
[Applause]
here's what I'm going to do tonight and
I don't take a lot of time for a
presentation so I know it has on the
sheet that it's 7 30 to 9 o'clock but I
can guarantee you you'll be dancing
before nine o'clock is here
the first what I want to do is just
start out by giving a little background
on what holography is
how lasers work and how
holography has changed within the last
six to eight weeks I've also brought a
number of holograms with me as I've
mentioned earlier from my own lab which
is in Allentown Pennsylvania and from a
lot a lot anyone in Allentown
people now say hello there
Aladdin we're away and also a lab down
in Virginia
and I made a special hologram for all of
you that are here today because I know
you had a speaker here for the Kennedy
assassination which was very interesting
I had an opportunity to go in and listen
off and on because I find it a little
fascinating myself but there was a
researcher named Jerry Robertson and he
sent me two bullets
uh that were fired from the same type of
rifle which is a I don't know if I'm
going to pronounced this Rifle right but
it's a men liquor cartano or something
like that rifle that Oswald used yeah
and they did an experiment by shooting
one of the bullets into a
Rift of a corpse
now I got these bullets from him and I
made a hologram and brought the Hologram
in for you to take a look at this
evening as well
and it's just an indication in forensic
science how holography gives us the
opportunity or someday will give us the
opportunity to take a look at evidence
uh without having the evidence leave
protective storage for instance there's
a number of different crimes that are
committed and there's a murder weapon
that maybe there's a few maybe there's a
few things that's very interesting about
this murder weapon something real
strange about it and there's a couple
different experts maybe across the
country or around the world who could
look at that and come to some sort of
determination about what what it's all
about in the normal process they would
either have to fly to an area to examine
it or under very protective conditions
if it's a high profile case
the object would be carried by
detectives to them by making
three-dimensional laser Holograms and
you'd have an opportunity of actually
making many many copies and say sending
it to many people both across the
country and around the world and they
can look at the evidence and see it as
if it's right in front of them some of
the Holograms that you'll have an
opportunity to see tonight you're going
to really think that what's in front of
you is there but there's nothing there
at all it's just a three-dimensional
holographic image for medical holography
I bought a hologram that was made by a
friend of mine at the Veterans
Administration Hospital down in New
Orleans
working on putting Holograms into
medical books for students so that when
they go back to their dorms at night to
study they can open their textbooks up
and have a three-dimensional holographic
image float above the page which they
can interact with
I personally had one called the
holographic heart which you could take
an instrument and go right up inside the
different chambers in the heart and do
measurements as it floated above the
Hologram I couldn't find it I think I
have it at Lehigh in a box somewhere but
I bought a different one which is a a
fetus with spina bifida and it will
allow you to see the
curvature of the spine very clearly and
from different angles something that
traditional photography would never be
able to give you an opportunity to do
so we've got a few Holograms to take a
look at but what I want to start off is
just to talk a little bit about where
holography was for those of you who are
not familiar with holography it's a
Imaging technique that's been around for
many many years and the theories
actually go back to 47 1948 with Dr
Dennis Deboer from the Imperial College
of London who actually invented
holography to increase the resolving
power of the electron microscope he
didn't have anything in mind when it
came to putting holograms on Frosted
Flakes or Corn Pops or anything like
that at the time it was something a lot
different than what it finally wound up
to be
in 1971 he received the Nobel Prize in
physics for holography and we've always
heard a lot about the promise of this
field if any of you have followed
holography from going back into the 60s
I I saw my first hologram in 68. we've
always heard about the promise of
holography that someday we'll be able to
have entertainment in the middle of the
room with lasers watch the Super Bowl
and have the players running around
white in the middle of the room
three-dimensionally we'll watch uh
ballet or our arts and different things
like that on on the shows
nothing of that ever came I mean where
is solography where do you see it how
many people have seen a hologram today
it's not an everyday experience for
everyone like most of the media like
television radio and things like that
basically due to the fact that what we
need to do is we need to have technology
catch up with holography holography is
ready to go despite what some of the
Articles say about holography that its
time has passed and it had promise but
it no longer has promise holography is
ready to go as soon as the technology
that will be able to transport it there
is ready currently with fiber optic
technology it would take 72 hours to
transmit one thirtieth of a second of
holographic information using fiber
optics now if you know if you're sitting
down watching a television or a
performance you're looking at 30 frames
per second
so if it takes 72 hours to transmit 1
30th of a second you have to times that
72 hours by 30.
and then what you would see would flash
on the screen for one second and you'd
have to wait that same amount of time
before the next second would flash on
the screen that's where we are with
technology but holography itself is
ready to go and they're doing a lot of
very interesting work at MIT Steve
Benton at the spatial Imaging group
working with compression techniques and
compression is going to probably be the
answer for us and the internet is really
helping us out with that because nowhere
is compression needed more than trans
transmission of data over our lines the
holography was always created using
traditional lasers and what I'd like to
do is I have a couple laser tubes here
and uh how about if I start one on one
side of the room and if it does make its
way all the way back you can just
continue to pass it around and if you
don't get an opportunity to see this and
you're interested in seeing one of these
tubes I will have them up here after the
presentation is over this is a typical
laser tube the helium neon laser it's
basically the lasers are called the way
that they're called because of if they
happen to be a gas laser of the gas
that's inside the actual laser argon
lasers have Argon gas inside Krypton
lasers have Krypton gas this is one of
the probably one of the most inexpensive
lasers that you can purchase it's a
helium neon laser and you can pick up a
five milliwatt helium neon laser which
is very low power that's 5 000 of one
watt so picture a one watt light bulb
and how dim that is this is five
thousandths of that
you'll notice the outsides made out of
glass it's a pretty sturdy tube you'll
see a smaller glass tube running down a
lot in the larger glass tube about the
size of a drinking straw that you get
with a soda and it's inside that small
glass tube where the gas is contained
inside of that tube and the mixture of
helium and neon
and you'll notice like the gentleman
over there that on the ends of the tube
we have these two little button type
things about this a little bit smaller
than the size of M M's and they're
actually mirrors and what happens is
when we apply power to this tube that
helium neon tube inside begins to Glow
just like a neon Pizza sign that you see
when you go out at night
and because we have the mirrors on the
ends of the tube what actually happens
is the light begins to reflect back and
forth between the two mirrors it
actually bounces back and forth and it
amplifies itself just like when we take
sound and we amplify it or we take power
and we amplify it and one of the mirrors
is close to 100 percent reflective or
theoretically close enough for me to say
100 reflective which means when the
light comes down and Strikes this mirror
100 of it or all of it bounces back up
or is reflected back up through the tube
again nothing exits out of this end of
the tube at all
the other mirror on the other hand is
only partially reflective we're around
98 reflective which means when the light
bounces from this mirror down to this
one this mirror excuse me is only going
to reflect 98 of the light back
the other two percent is actually going
to come through as the laser beam and in
a nutshell outside of the fact that
these mirrors have to be placed at an
exact multiple of whatever wavelength of
light the laser produces it's basically
all there is to it there's not a lot to
this as you will see when it gets passed
around
and traditionally with holography that's
the way Holograms have always been made
with gas lasers or solid-state lasers
like Ruby lasers pulsed Ruby lasers if
you've ever seen a holographic portrait
of someone chances are it was done using
what's called a pulsed Ruby laser and
this laser is actually a solid state
laser not solid state in the electronic
sense but a solid state that we used to
call it because it has a solid Ruby tube
that runs down a ruby Crystal Rod that
runs down the middle of the laser itself
and around that Ruby Crystal Rod is a
Xeon tube very similar to the very high
power flash tubes that you see
photographers use and when they flash
that Xeon tube it actually makes the
atoms in the Ruby laser throw off
photons of light and the end of the Ruby
tubes are actually mirrored just like
the mirrors are attached to this one
only the actual Ruby Rod itself the ends
are mirrored and the light bounces back
and forth and it comes out it's not a
continuous wave laser it's actually a
pulsed laser and the pulse is very quick
20 nanoseconds which is 20 billionths of
one second and just to give you some
sort of an idea how quick that is if you
were to take an F-14 fighter jet going
Full Throttle through the sky
in 29 seconds that jet would only move
forward a fraction of one of its atoms
that's how fast this flashes in fact the
flash is so fast that you never see it
and only remember it
Because by the time the signal goes from
the eye to the brain the flash is
already over so what you're seeing is
the memory of The Flash it's already
over that's how quick it is and
essentially what it does is it freezes
time it literally takes a slice and
freezes time because you cannot do live
subjects in a hologram traditionally
using lasers there are some other
methods where we can use
photographic film or Motion Picture film
first and then transfer that onto what's
called a stereogram but using lasers you
cannot have any vibration whatsoever in
your system
if anything on your system when you're
making a hologram vibrates more than a
fraction of a wavelength of light you
have no hologram whatsoever
and it makes it for a very strange field
because if you've ever been in a
holography studio to do a hologram
you'll know that the lights go out
heating is turned off air conditioning
is turned off all sounds there are no
sounds whatsoever and you stand there
and you become very still and quiet
before you do the exposure it's almost a
then like experience because they're any
type of noise even just someone talking
quietly in the lab
if it's vibrating your eardrum it's
certainly going to vibrate that
holographic plate
well how should I put this I'll just
come right out and say it a lot of times
F the FBI and other agencies like that
when they want to find out what it is
that you're talking about they can take
a laser which operates in the infrared
part of the Spectrum which your eye is
not sensitive to
and they can shine that Beam on your
window in your house or wherever you
happen to be
and as you speak and as I'm speaking in
this room everything in this room right
now is vibrating the walls the floor the
chandeliers everything is vibrating and
when you speak inside your house your
windows vibrate and what happens is when
that infrared laser beam that you cannot
even see is on your window and you speak
the window actually modulates the laser
beam so what they do is they read that
modulation that's being reflected off of
your window they can amplify that and
send it through an amp and here what it
is that you're saying just like when I
speak into the microphone the diaphragm
that's in the microphone is vibrating
the exact same thing is happening that's
what your window is functioning as a
diaphragm
a little while ago
I had a call from a friend of mine who
was going to be a guest on the show
named Steve Michael and Steve Michael
lives in Virginia
and he's been involved with holography
for many years back going back to the
60s actually
and he said to me
I have a laser pointer
and I've set up a little test with that
and it looks to me as if I could make a
hologram with this laser pointer
now up until this point it had always
been thought that laser diodes or
semiconductor lasers or whatever the
term is that you're used to hearing
that you could not make Holograms using
these diodes
whole bands have to be made with an
instrument like a helium neon laser
which has what's called a long coherence
length
your coherence length is how long or how
deep you can make a hologram for
instance you can see a hologram may have
six inches of depth or eight inches of
depth that is due to the fact that the
laser has a long coherence length
with diode lasers semiconductor lasers
which you find in your laser pointers
it's been always thought that the
coherence length is about a millimeter
tiny
if you tried to do a hologram of a coin
using a laser diode you'd find out to be
able to get the surface of the coin but
you would not get any depth whatsoever
but according to Steve Michael's test he
set up something called an
interferometer which can allow you to
measure coherence length he says I think
I can make a hologram with this
he said let me put off coming on your
show until I can test this out
so he went into his lab and he started
working and he eventually made a
hologram using a laser pointer
I think he paid like 49 for the laser
pointer
he called me and he came on the show and
talked about it and I went out down to
eckerd's drugstore
which is a drugstore in my area in
Allentown area and I bought a laser
pointer for 7.99
and I bought that into the laboratory
and I set it up and I started to work
with it
and we managed to get a hologram from
the 7.99 laser pointer
so right away we started to announce
this
and in the scientific community
it's always been thought you cannot do
this I mean it's it's what they call it
what did they call it Sam was it
theoretically impossible
theoretically impossible to do this
so what I did is I went out and I bought
a bunch of them I started sending them
around the world
and I said I want you people to start
doing some whole grants with these laser
pointers and they started turning out
beautifully beautiful I took one now I
did an 8 by 10 hologram which is
considered a relatively large hologram
eight by ten for Holograms eight by ten
you're getting up fairly large and you
need a pretty powerful laser to expose
an 8x10 hologram and I didn't beautiful
eight by ten hologram of a piece of Carl
which had about eight inches of depth
going back into the Hologram itself and
was beautifully bright
so what's transpired over the last few
weeks six or eight weeks is uh I told
Steve I'm going to see how far we can
take this so I started doing multiple
color holography and we started doing a
lot of different types of holograms that
um
people wouldn't be able to accomplish
with a helium and neon laser in a
regular Laboratory
and what I want to do I work a lot with
kids I've been working with kids
maybe about 15 years or so started out
down to Franklin Institute in
Philadelphia I was at Liberty Science
Center for a while which is in North
Jersey and we wanted to open a science
center in the Lehigh Valley
and I got involved with them I left the
Franklin Institute and Liberty Science
Center go and I wanted to concentrate on
helping them get a jump start in the
Lehigh Valley and I saw this as a
wonderful opportunity to have kids get
involved making Holograms
and in fact
my daughter's here tonight and her
physics professor
is actually a student that I had in my
class back in the early 80s
and what I do is I don't bring a lot of
Fury in with the kids what I do is I
allow them to come in and experience
this thing as as something fun to do
we're going to see a little laser light
show that they put together for you I
told them I was coming here and we
worked on a Boston Pops piece where they
designed all the little laser patterns
and stuff for you so you'll be able to
see that in a few moments as well
there are still a lot of people that do
not believe that it's possible to do
this I had someone that just drove nine
hours down to my studio because he was
supposed to do a paper on lasers and
Holograms and he decided to do his paper
on what I've been doing with holography
and his Professor would not accept it
because his professor said that it's not
possible
to do this you can't do this in
holography and what he did is this
professor told him that if you can make
one of these Holograms
then I'll accept the paper
and what what he wanted to do first was
set up his own studio and I told him you
know it might be better for you just to
come down to the lab so he came down to
the lab and made one
I had a family come in from the New York
area
they brought their kids ranged in age
from maybe about fifth or sixth grade up
into high school they were five or six
kids they each made a hologram using
this new technology
and when they went back and they wanted
to start doing it on their own when they
called someone to order the materials
the person asked them what is this going
to be used for and when they told him he
told them that you can't do that
I have someone that's in the audience
tonight that came to see me who's from a
rather large research facility
he's from Bell labs and you saw you saw
the work on the web right
and when you when you spoke about this
to some of your fellow researchers what
did they say about it
it was impossible
so he came from Bell labs and he came to
my studio
and what did you find out
yeah so this
this is a whole new field of Photography
now there's there's several things that
this is going to allow us to do
number one it's going to allow young
students to get involved with holography
the Hologram that I show you of the
Kennedy assassination bullets was made
on a system not just a laser but a
system the entire laser holography
Optical system
cost thirty dollars
four by five inch beautiful now these
aren't making little Holograms that
you'd be ashamed to show someone these
are exhibit quality Holograms
entire Optical System including laser
thirty dollars
also for artists who want to get
involved in the field they like to work
and bless you they like to work with
bigger pieces they don't like small
pieces they like to create big Holograms
Sam and I are looking into working with
very high power diodes where we can
create large works that used to cost
maybe about ten thousand dollars to
create for one of them
um we think we can get that price down
quite a bit to do this type of work so
it's going to open it up it's going to
it's going to make a lot of changes in
holography and I don't think that
the laser manufacturers are probably
going to be very happy about it for
instance I have a what's called a 10
milliwatt laser
in a science catalog which some of you
may be familiar with
it costs one thousand
150 dollars for a 10 milliwatt laser
you can get a 10 milliwatt diode
pretty cheap isn't it the actual diode
itself you can probably pick up for
about 35 hours right
so you're comparing 1 650 down to thirty
five when the laser discs first came out
they all had
gas lasers inside of the LaserDisc
players even some of the early CD
players in fact I used to take them and
jump them and take the tubes out but
then they went to the diodes so if
you've got a LaserDisc player or CD
player or dvd even some of the
supermarket scanners would go for your
checkout lines they're all diets that
are in there now there's not too many
things that are using the tubes anymore
so what I'd like to do is I'm going to
turn some of the lights out and I'm
going to show you a laser beam I'm going
to pass it over your heads so you can
get a chance to see the beam itself
and what I will do after that is
introduce the little laser light show
that the kids did which runs for about
four minutes
and then after the four minutes you're
up with the laser light show I will set
up the three-dimensional Holograms up
here for you to take a look at so that
you can come up and see the Holograms
themselves all of these Holograms were
made with a laser pointer